welcome back to episode two of our
chocolate series
now we went to oxford cue some drone
footage
and whilst we were there oh just in case
you don't know a lot of harry potter was
filmed in oxford hence you know the
hoodie
um
my wife is wearing an opposing one she's
a hufflepuff you know can't have
everything anyway
whilst we were there we walked around
the shops looked at chocolatiers we went
to gelaterias we went to ice cream shops
we had a hideous day eating lots of
chocolate based things whilst we were
there we discussed with one retailer
their gelato issues and one of them was
that they couldn't make
a chocolate gelato that either suited
everybody which is impossible but they
just really struggle with the texture so
they now don't sell that
as this is the chocolate ice cream
series
we're gonna get into
all of this hideous chocolatiness
so first i'm gonna do talk about cocoa
powder
first things first what exactly is cocoa
powder how is it made
so cocoa powder is made by
much like chocolate is you take the
beans they're fermented in the warmer
weather usually in the forest regions
once they're fermented they're then
cracked dried oven roasted and then
they're machined down into a semi-liquid
paste for
cocoa powders
at that stage they're compressed to
remove the bulk of the cocoa butter
which is the fat element to it then
what's left is dried and that becomes
cocoa powder that's what it is
we've got some here we touched on these
last week so we're going to bring some
in
show you what they look like and then do
a little taste test we're going to use
these three this is a new one that i
really wanted to try this is design true
dark this one is urca this is an italian
brand i think it's used in gelato a lot
over there and then obviously a very
well used pack of caliber
cocoa powder let's get some scooped
spoon i don't scoop this this isn't ice
cream this is cocoa powder we're going
to spoon some out onto here so we can
compare the color
[Music]
now interestingly
the true dark which is this one
the dazan
pronunciation side
is the lightest one in color
the urca is the darkest one
which is actually one of the lower fat
contents and then the caliber is
somewhere in between which is 24
but so
the name is almost irrelevant it's how
it is produced and the color that it
gives you for various different reasons
how the beans are roasted will dictate
the kind of color that you get and
obviously where the beans are from
originally i know calabo say on the back
of their pack that they use
yeah caliber use west african beans
means nothing to me unfortunately
i can't read the back of that it's in
italian but you know
these ones
many unbearable hours later absolutely
no idea anyway it doesn't say on the
back of that pack where the beans are
from but it's the 10 to 12
so
the different fat contents do somehow
relate to the different colors
but not always
this darkest one is
lower fat content than this one
they're all 100 cocoa when they say that
it just means they're made from pure
cocoa beans it means there's no
additives in there
so how do they taste what we're going to
do is we're going to warm this milk up
mix some of these in ideally with cocoa
powder you should bloom it to bring the
flavor out forward but we don't have
time to do that for each one that means
cooking each mix for you know a couple
of minutes just to bring it up to
temperature but that's what microwaves
are for so it's a quick transition and
we'll come back to it now
[Music]
wait's not one knot
so we've mixed these in to hot milk
and you can see there's quite a
difference in color
and actually the color
isn't really indicative of how the
powders are so this one here which is
the true dark which is a 10 to 12
percent fat
sedan
it's actually darker than
the caliber which is 24
it's not as dark as the erka which is 22
to 24
so the color
isn't quite as straightforward
this is something that we touched on in
the last episode of this chocolate
series
the reason chocolate ice cream is so
difficult to make is because you want
the color you want the intensity of
flavor and you want to be able to
control the fat content
so why we've done this it highlights one
thing color
now we're going to taste these and see
which one really punches out with that
chocolate flavor
it's a very familiar flavor the caliber
i use it all the time
it's quite well rounded it's not
particularly bitter
the the punch from the cocoa powder
itself
is subtle
and something i found over using calibo
cocoa powder
is you do have to put quite a lot in
to make it really chocolatey
onto the erka
a much stronger punch of chocolate
flavour coming through
slightly lower fat content
but it's a much darker color as well
when you compare the two the color of
the orca is you know 25 darker
so
just for those two alone if you really
want a punch from your chocolate ice
cream the erka would be the one to go if
you want a more subtle approach to a
chocolate ice cream then the caliber
would be the one to go and finally we're
going to try
this the design the new one
now that's actually got quite a milky
apart from the fabulous maple milk it's
got quite a milk chocolate taste to it
the flavor comes through with the same
strength and intensity as the calibo
does it's not as strong a tasting as
this one but interestingly enough the
color is like i said before darker than
the caliber one so this ends up
somewhere in between those two as far as
flavor and color intensity goes
if you were to take this one 10 to 12
fat it would have quite a different
effect to your ice cream compared to
either of these two which are almost
twice as much fat in
so now that we've identified that
there's
problems with just picking out a cocoa
powder and using that in your ice cream
we're going to go on to the actual
chocolate element
something i get asked a lot about is
whether it's better to use physical
chocolate or cocoa powder for chocolate
ice cream or various different types of
chocolate ice cream there is no right or
wrong answer here they produce different
results but for different reasons
quality of chocolate physical chocolate
much like the cocoa powder is more
important
than the fat percentage or intensity of
the physical chocolate itself
so
let's take this which is the possibly
the cheapest chocolate you're ever going
to eat apart from hershey's
and let's just
try some of it
[Music]
i'm sure every single bar of that has
that really fake golden ticket but fun
all the same
so
this smells
that's just surprisingly strong
i'd say this is somewhere in the 40
ish mark
and it tastes foul
it's not pleasant chocolate at all
it's got a really artificial taste to it
which doesn't surprise me because it's
you know it probably cost about one
pence to make that
so
we've got some good quality chocolate in
front of us we've got caliber 70
here
we've got white chocolate and we'll
again get around to that again in a
minute
and then we've got two new chocolates to
us and these are the burema
milk chocolate and
medium dark or semi-sweet chocolate
i love the little small callout size i
mean look how tiny wee that small little
bit of chocolate is
what does this taste like
it's really nice it's a well-balanced
chocolate it's not overly bitter which
is kind of what you'd expect in the 50
range we have
another one
which is in the 50 range
so this this
56 this one is 55
it's basically the same
how do the two compare
now bacolade is actually good good
quality chocolate
but this
bureau chocolate has got a much stronger
natural flavor to it it doesn't have any
bitter aftertones to it so i'm really
i'm really impressed with this stuff
they do the milk version
so let's try some of that
very smooth taste
let's try the baccalaureate
same percentage coke solids
the barimus head and shoulders above the
back leg milk chocolate
it's totally different it's a completely
different ballpark because you know kind
of you you're
touching into baking at home kind of
chocolate but this is
very professional gray chocolate
so
this is going to be my new go-to for
milk chocolate white chocolate
technically not chocolate
now if you're going to
use this in ice cream there's a there's
a lot of things you have to do
it's a really strong overpowering
sweetness
the amount of sugar that is in this
is off the chart compared to all the
others we'll talk about that in a minute
and finally is the 70
calorie chocolate
we know it's a very nice strong
chocolate taste it has that bitterness
as you'd expect because it's at 70 range
if you want to use chocolate and ice
cream which one would you start with
making chocolate ice cream now we've
established some difference in taste of
the cocoa powders and the chocolates
which one do you want to use it's
certainly not going to be this one
start with the chocolate that you enjoy
the taste of i mean you do get a golden
ticket but you know can't have
everything
so
we know that
me personally
i prefer these burema chocolates over
the baccalade
i don't dislike bacolade chocolate but
out of the two
these two win out
white chocolate
is a very different type of ice cream
so we'll just move that aside for the
minute and come into this one so we've
got three different types chocolate here
we've got our milk chocolate
our semi-sweet and then our dark
now if you're gonna make a chocolate ice
cream most people will automatically go
for the chocolate that they like to eat
so if you like milk chocolate you'll
go for a milk chocolate but the dairy in
ice cream dulls flavors by a huge amount
so if you used this very nice tasting
milk chocolate you'd get a really dull
milky chocolate ice cream it wouldn't
have really any flavor punch whatsoever
so you'd go up
to the 50 range because once the flavor
of that is dulled down by the dairy
you're actually going to end up where
the milk flavor is so that's likely
where you want to start
and then that goes the same if you want
a semi-sweet finish you'd go up
to the 70
because that is where you'll end up once
the dairy has the dulling effect on the
flavor
now if you want to create this 70
this is where you get into the cocoa
powders you also do have you know 100
percent cacao
i'm not gonna try this it's incredibly
strong if you want to see me try this
and you want to see me make an ice cream
with this like and subscribe and comment
down below and maybe i'll make a video
down the line in this chocolate series
so physical chocolate has less of an
intense chocolate flavor in your ice
cream if you really want a punch you go
to the cocoa powders
a little bit about white chocolate is
it's mostly sugar so let's just get the
pack quickly
when we look at the back we see 55
sugar
and if we look at this which is the
caliber
on here it's 26 sugar
the burema 56 is
42 sugar and then their milk is 49 sugar
so these are all
got sugar and a lot of it in there per
weight cocoa powders have none
basically there's a small amount of
sugar which is actually in the cocoa
pods coconuts themselves and that's a
natural base but you're looking at sub 1
so it's basically none
so if you're gonna make ice cream you
need to account for the sugars that are
in the chocolate that you use
cocoa powder you don't have any sugar in
there so you have to add it all after
next week we're gonna make
not next week
next episode we're gonna make actual ice
cream so we're gonna make
one from this which is
the berima 56
and
i think we're gonna go for
erka which is the dark cocoa powder 22
to 24
and then we'll compare them to the
physical elements when they're made
anyway
thanks very much for watching this which
is the next
scientific part of our chocolate ice
cream series if you missed the first
part of it i'll put a link below don't
forget to like and subscribe and we'll
see you next week